Charles Ulen Pickrell papers, 1891-1962 (bulk 1940-1961)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Charles Ulen Pickrell papers, 1891-1962 (bulk 1940-1961)
AZ 298
Pickrell, Charles Ulen, 1892-1962
This collection includes personal and official correspondence, photographs, articles, speeches, clippings, notes and related material on cowboys, Arizona pioneers, cattle industry and agriculture.
5.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Charles U. Pickrell was a livestock specialist and was Director of the University of Arizona Agricultural Extension Service from 1937-1958.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Personal Materials, 1911-1962
Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1962
Series III: South Africa Travel Material, 1952-1954
Series IV: Ranch Life Materials, 1940-1961
Series V: University of Arizona Agricultural Extension Service and the College of Agriculture, 1891-1962
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes personal and official correspondence, photographs, articles, speeches, clippings, notes and related material on cowboys, Arizona pioneers, cattle industry and agriculture. It includes clippings from son Robert W. Pickrell's campaign for State Attorney General, 1960; some records of the Extension Service, including staff rosters, 1891-1958; photographs of cattle, sheep, and unidentified pioneers; materials from 1952 South Africa trip as consultant to British Government on economic development and cattle production; and manuscript material for a history on the University's College of Agriculture. It also includes cowboy poems by Bruce Kiskaddon, printed on Los Angeles Union Stock Yards calendars, 1941- 1959, and research on cattle brands.
Kiskaddon, Bruce, 1878-1950; Pickrell, Robert Wallace, 1922-; Pickrell family; University of Arizona. College of Agriculture; University of Arizona. Agricultural Extension Service; University of Arizona. Agricultural Experiment Station; University of Arizona -- History; University of Arizona -- Faculty; Cowboys -- Poetry; Cattle trade -- Arizona; Pioneers -- Arizona; Cattle brands -- Arizona; South Africa -- Agriculture -- Economic aspects; Arizona -- Politics and government; Correspondence; Photographs
Separated Material
Maps received with the collection were removed and cataloged separately.
Container List
- Series I: Personal Materials, 1911-1962
  - Biographical material. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Charles Pickrell). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arizona State University (Charles Pickrell, class of 1911). (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - World War I: Photographs and miscellaneous items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - World War I: Letters to Anne Wallace. 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - University of Arizona appointments. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Honors and awards. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memberships. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Philanthropy. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of family and friends. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal purchases. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal miscellany. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: Charles Pickrell 1922-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings: Anne Wallace Pickrell (also photos and personal items). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Robert Pickrell political campaign and career. 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Pioneers. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Legal papers regarding property; miscellaneous financial records. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Article: "Hashknife Story." 1931 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Article: "Setting America's Table." 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Article: "May Day." 1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Article: "A Rugged Son of Arizona," Smoke Signal. May 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Article: Miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Article: 4-H Club work (proposed). 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Books: notes, lists and correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Prayers. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Health: personal material and clippings on diet. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Humor (mostly clippings). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Shop." (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Songs and poems. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes and notebooks. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Talk: Cowboys and cattle industry. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Talk: Arizona history. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Talk: Various pioneers. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Talk: Early irrigation history. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Talk: Agriculture and farming. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Talk: Extension work and 4-H Clubs. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Talk: Arizona Historical Convention. March 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Talk: George W. Hennessey Banquet. March 22, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cowboy notes. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Various historical notes. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Salt River Valley historical notes. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Stories" (mostly about pioneers). (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1943-1962
  - Correspondence: Arizona Cattle Feeders' Association. 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Arizona Cattle Growers' Association. 1944-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Arizona Water Resources Committee. 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Arizona Wool Growers Association. 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Amhurst, Henry Fountain. 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Cline, George & Walter. 1953-1961 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes an article by Charles Pickrell: "A Top Hand Leaves Us," Arizona Cattlelog, May 1959.
  - Correspondence: Ellinwood, Tom. 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Fannin, Governor Paul J. 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Goldwater, Barry. 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Governor's Advisory Board of the Area Redevelopment Act. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Governor's Committee on Arid Lands. 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Gyberg, Frank. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Hayden, Carl. 1952-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Heffner, Harry. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes a transcript of an interview with Charles Pickrell
  - Correspondence: Homestead Lands. 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Jobes, Harry C. 1952-1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Mack, Mabel C. 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Northern Arizona Cattlemen's Association. 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Orme, Charles and family. 1955-1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Osborn, Governor Sidney P. 1945 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Parker, Charles Franklin. 1944-1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Parker, Charles Franklin. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Includes an article about Charles Pickrell by Charles Parker entitled "Teller of True Tall Tales," Arizona Highways, October 1961 and fan mail to Charles Pickrell.
  - Correspondence: Pickrell, Charles U., Jr. (son). (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Pickrell, James (son). (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Pickrell, Robert (son). (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Pickrell, Watson (father). (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: W. W. "Bill" (brother). (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Pickrell, William Smith and family (cousins). (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous Pickrell family. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Pyle, Howard. 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Rhodes, John J. 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Ridgeway, William (talk given at meeting of Westerners). June 1, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Shute, G. W. 1953-1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Includes revised article, "Pleasant Valley War," taken from Arizona Cattlelog, April 1956.
  - Correspondence: Thornburg, Wayne. 1942-1961 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Udall Family. 1946-1961 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Wallace Family (in-laws). (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Webb Family. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Includes reprint of articles from Arizona Cattlelog.
  - Correspondence: Westerners. 1957-1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Williams, Jack. 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Yavapai Cattle Growers. 1958-1962 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes a talk by Charles Pickrell at the 1961 annual meeting.
  - Correspondence: General. 1943-1962 (Box 7, Folder 4-9)
- Series III: South Africa Travel Material, 1952-1954
  - Correspondence. 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Reports. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Passport. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Background material. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Talks. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Ranch Life Materials, 1940-1961
  - Cattle photographs. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Cattle brands. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Clippings of cowboys. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Farm and ranch directories. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Saddle catalogs. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Horse photographs. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Horse pictures and drawings. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Sheep and burro photographs. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Western paintings (correspondence, etc.). (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - J. R. Williams Cartoons: "Skull Valley" and "Out Our Way." (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Bruce Kiskaddon: Cowboy Poems (from the Los Angeles Union Stockyard's Monthly Livestock Letter). (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Pioneer photographs. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series V: University of Arizona Agricultural Extension Service and the College of Agriculture, 1891-1962
  - Agriculture Extension Service, 1891-1962
    - Correspondence: General. 1940-1962 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence: Harvill, President Richard A. 1957-1961 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Acres in Irrigated Counties. 1960 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Staff meeting minutes. 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Travel expense account. 1943/44-1961/62 (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
    - Dean Harold E. Myers miscellaneous material. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous material. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Staff rosters. 1891-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Facts of Arizona Agriculture and Background, A-Z." (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 4-H Clubs. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Statistics. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Charles Pickrell's notes on various agricultural topics. (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - Charles Pickrell's notes on topics by Byron Shaw (excerpts from speeches, publications, etc.). (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - History of the College of Agriculture
    - Correspondence regarding the "History." (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - History of the College of Agriculture: (p. 1-53-?), draft. (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - History of the College of Agriculture: various versions. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - History of the College of Agriculture: miscellaneous notes, outlines, lists, background material. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Experiment Station, farms, sub-stations, extension work. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Faculty and Staff: list. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Faculty and Staff: Individual records. (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
    - Faculty and Staff: Robert H. Forbes. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Research notes dictated by Charles Pickrell. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Resident Instruction in Agriculture. (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Home Economics. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Departments and Activities: drafts. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Departments and Activities: Final. (Box 13, Folder 10)